Guide to the Paul Percy Parker Collection, 1782-1936
Department of Special Collections
Paul Percy Parker Collection,
1782-1936
Special Collections M066
Parker, Paul Percy
.75 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Paul P. Parker, 1963.
BIOGRAPHY
Paul Percy Parker was a newspaperman in California'a Salinas Valley.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Parker Collection of Californiana contains official documents (many in Spanish), legal and financial papers, manuscripts of narratives and memoirs, printed material and clippings relative to California history. The major bulk of the papers are dated prior to 1900 and the total span is from 1782-1936. They deal primarily with the Monterey area, the Salinas Valley, Salinas, San Jose, and the lower Peninsula area.
The Spanish and Mexican California documents are of special interest and include the signatures of José de Zuñiga, José Figueroa, Simeon Castro, David Spence, Luis del Castillo Negrete and an unsigned letter by Manuel Micheltorena. The William S. Johnson material contains a number of papers concerning land grant property and there are some other title papers and transfers on this subject. There are a few documents by Walter Colton and a lot of material on the Salinas Lettuce Strike of 1936.
CONTAINER LIST
- SPANISH & MEXICAN CALIFORNIA OFFICIAL DOCUMENTS 1782-1848 (Box 1, Folder 1.)
  - 1. 1782.Signed by José de Zuñiga, official under Gov. Felipe de Neve. re: supplies from San Blas. 2 pp.
  - 2. 1783.Signed by José de Zuñiga. 2 pp.
  - 3. 1832, Dec.Signers: Salvador Espinosa, José Estrada, Santiago Moreno, José Castro, José Antonio [Gaxiola), José Joaquin Gomez, Bonifacio de Madriaga. Certified Feb. 23, 1835by [Luis] del Castillo Negrete, and Dav[id] Spence. 3 PP
  - 4. 1833, Jul. 16.Signed by José Figueroa. 2 pp.
  - 5. 1833.Outline of sword. Evidence in murder trial.
  - 6. 1836, Dec. 28.re: David Espensa (Spence), Estevan Munras, Feodoro Gonzales, José Ramon Estrada, José Joaquin Gomez. Signed Nov. 29, 1838(docketed 1836) by Simeon Castro. 3 pp.
  - 7. [1834 or 39], Feb. 28.Signed Juan de Castro. 1 P.
  - 8. 1841.Signed (Tomas] Pacheco - Juan de Castro, official at San Jose. 1 p.
  - 9. 1841, Jan. 8.Seal or initial unidentified. at San Juan. 1 p.
  - 10. 1841, Jan. 8.Seal or initial unidentified. Name of Manuel Larios appears. 1 p.
  - 11. 1841, Apr. 23.Seal or initial unidentified. at San Jose, name of [Juan Bautista] Alvarado appears. 1 p.
  - 12. 1841, Oct. 16.Schooner :Nymph" to James Robenson. bill. 2 pp.
  - 13. 1844, May 2.Signed Rafael Pinta. 1 p.
  - 14. 1846.General [Manuel Micheltorena] to Estevan de la Torre. Mentions Feliciano Soberanes. 2 pp.
  - 15. 1846, Jan 24.Signed J. S. Escamilla, Manuel Dias Y Garcia. 2 ppe
  - 16. 1846, Apr. 10.Signed Antonio Mendez. 1 p.
  - 17. 1846, Apr. 19.John Townsend (Monterey Council) to Thomas Kittleman (Sheriff) - orders to summon grand jury. 2 pp.
- DR. MANUEL QUIXANO IN MONTEREY. 1807-1825 (Box 1, Folder 1A.)
  Recent, typed account by unknown author. Includes information on murder of Padre Andres Quintana. 2 pp.
- BOOK OF SOLARES OF MONTEREY COUNTY PUEBLOS. 1828 (Box 1, Folder 2.)
  Translation Ms by William S. Johnson in 1851,note by Parker.
- HARTNELL CENSUS OF CALIFORNIA RANCHOS. 1836, Photostats from Vallejo Documents at Bancroft Library. (Box 1, Folder 3.)
- WILLIAM S. JOHNSON PAPERS. 1840-188_. (See Bancroft, IV, 694.) (Box 1, Folder 4.)
  - 1. 1840, Dec. 30.Goodwin, Thomas I. to John P. Flagg. 3 pp.
  - 2. 1852, Jun. 24.Conveyance of pueblo San Juan Bautista. Signed [Hilario] Ortez, José [Maria] Sanchez, Nicolas Butron, Miguel Castro, and Antonio Lima. Certified by W. S. J. 3 pp.
  - 3. 1856, Jan. 22.Decree of Confirmation. Certified on Jul. 9, 1869by Sherman Day. 2 pp.
  - 4. 1859, May 22.Transfer. Signed Cirilo Basso, José A. Sepulveda. José Bernal. 1 p. in Spanish.
  - 5. 1864, Aug. 20.Newspaper clippings
  - 6. 1865, May 10.Agreement at Natividad. Johnson, W. S. and Francisco Rico. Witness: Manuel A. Castro. 4 pp.
  - 7. 1869, Apr. 2.Indenture (mining and water rights). Woodside, P. K. to William Wiggins. Certified by John Gorman, Nevada Mining Commissioner on same date; Warren T. Lockhart, Lauder County, Nevada Recorder, on May 6, 1869;seal dated Jun. 10, 1869.6 pp.
  - 8. 1869, Aug. 13.Indenture (land lease). Soberanes, [Paufilo] to Manuel Lorenzo Martinez (part of Rancho Soledad). Recorded and sealed by W. S. J. and Ed. W. Mills. 4 pp.
  - 9. 1869, Nov. 30.[Soto], J. M. to Murphy, Grant & Co. Sight draft. 1 p
  - 10. 1871, Jun. 22.Agreement. Murphy, John M, and P. H. Sheridan. Recorded by W. S. J. 4 pp.
  - 11. 188_, Nov. 27.Johnson, F. P. to Johnson & Browne. Financial note. 1 p.
  - 12. 188-, Apr. 2,Bodie Lodge No. 279 I.O.O.F., Bodie, Calif. Bill. 1 p.
- MRS. W. S. JOHNSON (LOUISA CANO). - "HERBS AND HOW TO USE THEM" (Box 1, Folder 5.)
  Typed transcript of herb list by Parker.
- JOHN D. ACKERMAN, SR. - "MY FIRST TRIP TO CALIFORNIA" 1843-47 (Box 1, Folder 5A.)
  Recent, typed copy of a letter or article and note by J. D. Ackerman, Jr. 3 pp.
- YGNACIO PEDRO VILLEGAS. (Box 1, Folder 6.)
  "Wrote his Memoirs and other articles after he became station agent at Soledad in May, 1876, at that time the end of the Southern Pacific system. He was born in Mexico and came to California via 'carreta' before the discovery of gold. He was related to Don Francisco Pacheco and lived with them at the San Felipe rancho in San Benito County. A very bright boy, he soon spoke English and talked with miners and immigrants. He wrote about everything he saw and described life on the ranchos."
  -Parker
  - 1. Memoirs from before 1849. Typed with Mss corrections. (May have been published). 30 pp.
  - 2. Fictional Romance. "containing information that could not be put in Memoirs". Typed with Mss corrections. 45 pp. Duplicates 4 pp. Parker notes 1 p.
- WALTER COLTON. 1846-1847, "in Colton's hand" (Box 1, Folder 7.)
  - 1. 1846, Sept. 24.Monterey Municipal Regulation. 1 P.
  - 2. 1846, Oct. 10.I.O.U. Soto, Joaquin to Ricardo Forcado. Witness: William R. Gardner.
  - 3. 1847, Jun. 18.Police Ordinance. 1 p.
  - 4. 1847, Sept. 24.Magistrative Ordinance in Spanish and English. 2 pp.
- R. FREDERICK A. MacDOUGALL (McDOUGAL or MacDOUGAL) - ANZAR GUARDIANSHIP PAPERS. 1854-1871 (Box 1, Folder 8.)
  'In 1853, Juan Miguel Anzar died. He held title to land grants "Aromas", 13,218 acres; "Quien Sabe", 17,636 acres; and "Real de Los Aquilas", 30,856 acres. Dr. MacDougal (sic) was appointed guardian of the three minor children. His guardianship papers give a very accurate account of running three large ranches up to 1869: the buying and selling of live stock, wages paid for all kinds of help, when the fence law went into effect, the surveying, pickets, nails, lumber, etc., here in detail; education of the boys, clothing them and the food they ate; medicines, taxes.'
- DANIEL R. MARTIN - PERSONAL REMINISCENCES. [?1855-1874] (Box 1, Folder 8A.)
  Incidents in and about Monterey for an article in Parker's Historical Column in the "Salinas Jounnal" or the "Salinas Post". 6 pp.
- MONTEREY UNION LEAGUE AND HOME GUARD. Apr. 21, 1863-Dec., 1864 (Box 1, Folder 9.)
  "The Monterey Home Guards were organized to protect Monterey from the Confederates at the start of the Civil War. Constitution and By Laws, interesting meetings, roster of members which comprised the leading citizens of the city, including David Jacks."
  - 1. Minute book and notes by Parker.
- FEDERICO PONCIANO FELIZ - MONTEREY, CALIFORNIA SINCE 1868 (Box 1, Folder 9A.)
  - Typed lists and outline, perhaps for a book or long article. 8 pp.
- LAND GRANTS, TITLES, ETC. 1868-1886 (Box 1, Folder 10.)
  - 1. Cambuston, Henry - land grant case. Printed with Mss corrections. Seal and certification by George E. Whitney on Jul. 7, 1868.18 pp.
  - 2. Butron, Ramona and Jeremiah McMahon - Petition re: Natividad Rancho. Apr. 2, 1864,certified by E. F. Beale. 8 pp.
  - 3. Rancho San Joaquin or Rosa Morada - Abstract of Title of James McMahon. Certified by W. S. Johnson May 26, 1868.13 pp.
  - 4. Rancho San Felipe y Ansaymia - Draft of Abstract of Title of John W. Metcalf, Jul. 2, 1868.11 pp.
  - 5. City Lands of Monterey - Field Notes. Oct. 1868
    "David Jacks bought 29,698 acres from the City of Monterey for $1,002 in 1856. In 1896 the City of Monterey brought suit to recover, claiming fraud but lost case. The lands extended from Cypress Point along Monterey Bay shore line to mouth of Salinas river, thence east up river to within a mile of the now Salinas River bridge, thence south to Laguna Seca and west to Monterey Presidio".
  - 6. Rancho La Sagrada Familia or Bolsa del Potrero y Moro Cojo - Official translation of title papers and transfers to establish title by J. Alexander Forbes, Nov. 26, 1886.12 pp.
  - 7. Delgado, Christina - Petition of rights to Rincon de las Salinas, official copy and translation, certified by J. Alexander Forbes, Nov. 26, 1886.22 pp.
- SALINAS LETTUCE STRIKE. 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11.)
  - 1. Green, William, President of A. F. of L. "Communist Activities in the United States". Reprint from Congressional Record of Jun. 27, 1934of a report to the President of the U.S.
  - 2. Merriam, Frank F. - Speech, Aug., 1934.
  - 3. The American Plan, Jun., 1936.Published by the Industrial Association of San Francisco.
  - 4. Fruit & Vegetable Workers Union Bulletin, Salinas, Aug. 15, 1936.
  - 5. Special Bulletin, Sept. 8, 1936.
  - 6. Monterey Peninsula Herald, Monterey newspaper, Sept. 16, 1936.
  - 7. Monterey Peninsula Herald Sept. 17, 1936.
  - 8. Pacific Weekly, Carmel, Sept. 21, 1936.
  - 9. The American Citizen, San Francisco, Sept. 26, 1936.
  - 10. Canete, Rufo C., President of Filipino Labor Union. Broadside, Sept. 28, 1936.
  - 11. [Strike Official Bulletin], typed article dated Sept. 29, 1936.
  - 12. The Literary Digest, New York. Oct. 10, 1936.
  - 13. The American Citizen, San Francisco, Oct. 16, 1936.
  - 14. Monterey County Section - Communist Party of U.S.A., Broadside. n.d.
  - 15. Fruit & Vegetable Workers Union of California. Circular and duplicate. n.d.
  - 16. Industrial Association of San Francisco Bulletin. "copy of circular by District Committee of Cannery and Agricultural Workers (a Communist Unit)". n.d.
  - 17. Sinclair, Upton - typed excerpt from the "The Goslings". n.d.
- CLIPPINGS - HISTORICAL ARTICLES. (Box 1, Folder 11A.)
- MISCELLANEOUS. (Box 1, Folder 12.)
  - 1. Republican State Ticket, California, Sept, 6, 1872.
  - 2. I.W.W. Song Book, I.W.W. Publishing Bureau, Cleveland, Ohio. Jun., 1914, 7th edition.
  - 3. "Feliz Navidad, Amigos". Poem (?by Parker), n.d.
- SCRAPBOOK OF CLIPPINGS - articles on California history. (Box 2, Folder 13.)
- JOURNAL OF WAHRLICH & CORNETT, SALINAS, CALIFORNIA. (Box 3, Folder 14.)
  First general merchandise store in Salinas opened 1872.
  - Daily sales record, etc. Jun. 8, 1872-May 9, 1873.
SEPARATED MATERIALS
Books were placed in Special Collections and Stanfordiana was placed in the Stanford Collection.